[Men's Choir Singing in Welsh]
[Church Bell Ringing]
I am packing my belongings
in the shawl my mother
used to wear when
she went to the market,
and I am going from my valley,
and this time,
I shall never return.
I am leaving behind me
my 50 years of memory.
Memory.
Strange that the mind will
forget so much of what only
this moment has passed
and yet hold clear and bright
the memory of what
happened years ago,
of men and women
long since dead.
Yet who shall say what is real
and what is not?
Can I believe
my friends all gone
when their voices
are still a glory
in my ears?
No, and I will stand
to say no and no again,
for they remain
a living truth
within my mind.
There is no fence
nor hedge 'round time
that is gone.
You can go back and have
what you like of it
if you can remember.
So I can close my eyes
on my valley as it is today,
and it is gone,
and I see it as it was
when I was a boy.
Green it was
and possessed of
the plenty of the earth.
In all Wales,
there was none so beautiful.
Everything I ever
learnt as a small boy
came from my father,
and I never found
anything he ever told me
to be wrong or worthless.
The simple lessons
he taught me are as sharp
and clear in my mind
as if I had heard them
only yesterday.
In those days, the black slag,
the waste of the coal pits,
had only begun to cover
the side of our hill,
not yet enough to mar
the countryside
nor blacken the beauty
of our village,
for the colliery
had only begun
to poke its skinny black
fingers through the green.
I can hear even now the voice
of my sister Angharad.
♪ Huw ♪
♪ Angharad ♪
Coal miners were my father
and all my brothers,
and proud of their trade.
Gwilym Morgan, £3 and 7.
Thank you, sir.
Lanto Morgan, £3 and 7.
Ivor Morgan, £3 and 7.
Davy Morgan, £2 and 5.
Owen Morgan, £2 and 5.
Young Gwilym Morgan,
£1 and 10.
Someone would
strike up a song,
and the valley would ring
with the sound of many voices,
for singing is in my people
as sight is in the eye.
[Whistle Blows]
[Singing in Welsh]
Then came the scrubbing
out in the back yard.
It was the duty
of my sister Angharad
to bring the buckets
of hot water and cold,
and I performed
what little tasks I could,
as my father and brothers
scrubbed the coal dust
from their backs.
Most would come off them,
but some would stay for life.
This is the honorable badge
of the coal miner,
and I envied it on my father
and grown-up brothers.
Scrub and scrub,
Mr. Coal would lie
there and laugh at you.
Aah!
Oh!
There was always
a baron of beef
or a shoulder or leg of lamb
before my father.
There was never any talk
while we were eating.
I never met anybody
whose talk was better
than good food.
My mother
was always on the run,
always the last
to start her dinner
and the first to finish,
for if my father
was the head of our house,
my mother was its heart.
After dinner, when dishes
had been washed,
the box was brought
to the table
for the spending money
to be handed out.
No one in our valley
had ever seen a bank.
We kept our savings
on the mantelpiece.
My father used to say
that money was made
to be spent,
just as men
spend their strength
and brains in earning it,
and as willingly,
but always with a purpose.
Thank you, Dada.
Ha ha ha!
Out of the house
and across the street,
as I had run
a hundred times before.
[Bell Ringing]
Softly now, for respect
for chapel was the first
thing my father taught us.
Then straight to Mrs. Tossall,
the shop for that toffee
which you could
chew for hours,
it seems to me now,
and even after
it had gone down,
you could swallow
and still find the taste of it
hiding behind your tongue.
It is with me now,
so many years later.
[Doorbell Rings]
It makes me think of
so much that was good
that is gone.
It was on this afternoon
that I first saw Bron...
Bronwyn.
She had come over
from the next valley
for her first call
on my father and mother.
Is this Gwilym
Morgan's house?
You must be Huw.
Is that you, Bronwyn?
Yes.
There is lovely you are.
I think I fell in love
with Bronwyn then.
Perhaps it is foolish to think
a child could fall in love,
but I am the child that was,
and nobody knows
how I felt,
except only me.
I am so proud for Ivor.
I'm the one
to be proud.
You think well
of our Ivor?
Ha ha ha!
It seems only
a few months since he was
scratching around here
like this one
with his mouth open.
This is Bronwyn, Huw,
who's to be your sister.
We have met already.
Be careful of the basket.
There's shortcake in it.
This is not for you, Huw.
You will have your time
to come.
Run along.
[Singing in Welsh]
Oh!
Bronwyn and Ivor were
to be married by the new
preacher, Mr. Gruffydd,
who had come from
the university at Cardiff.
This was my first
sight of him.
[Singing in Welsh]
[Bell Ringing]
Yay!
[Laughter]
[Laughter Stops]
Oh!
♪ Now, here's a man
won't get drunk ♪
♪ Can't get drunk,
shan't get drunk ♪
♪ Here's a man
won't get drunk ♪
♪ Peter O'Pea ♪
♪ From my heel to my toe
from my toe to my knee ♪
♪ I'll walk the line,
jog the line... ♪
♪ Oh, P... ♪
Ohh.
Good evening,
Mr. Morgan.
Yes, indeed, sir.
Oh, excuse me.
Thank you.
Ahh.
[Singing in Welsh]
Come now, boys.
Back to work.
Ivor, find Dai Griffiths
and Idris John
and bring them
to Mr. Evans' office.
Will we come with you?
No. This is
for the older men.
Home to your mother.
But...
Leave it now, Davy.
Well, come! Come!
Why aren't you washed?
We were waiting for you.
The cut is only
a few shillings.
There will still be
plenty for all of us.
A bit of supper now,
is it, girl?
It is because
they are not getting
the old price for coal.
Come and wash now.
May... May we
speak first, sir?
Yes.
They did not give the
real reason for this cut.
We've been expecting it
since the ironworks
at Dowlais closed.
What have the ironworks
to do with us?
Their men came to the colliery
willing to work for any wage,
so our wages
must come down.
And this is only
the beginning.
Watch now, they'll cut us
again and still again,
until they have this,
as empty
as their promises.
Nonsense. A good worker
is worth good wages,
and he will get them.
Not while
there are three men
for every job.
Why should owners pay
more if men are willing
to work for less?
Because the owners
are not savages.
They are men,
like us.
Men, yes,
but not like us.
Would they deal with you
when you went to them?
No.
They have power,
and we have none.
How will we get power,
from the air?
No. From a union
of all the men.
Union, is it?
I never thought
I'd hear my own sons
talking socialist nonsense.
But it's sense,
good sense!
Unless
we stand together...
I've had enough
of this talk!
But, Father, it d...
Come and wash now.
Your good mother
will be waiting.
Do you think I'll let them
make my father stand
like a dog in the rain
and not raise
my hands to stop it?
Hisht, Davy.
Who gave you
permission to speak?
This is too important
for silence.
They're trying
to punish you...
It is not more important
than good manners.
What are we
going to do?
You'll die of the cold
when it comes to snow.
Let us stand together
and see how they act then.
Right. The men will come
if we say the word.
All the pits are ready.
You will not make me
a plank for your politics.
I will not be
the excuse
for any strike.
If they can do
things like that
to the spokesman,
what will they try
and do to the men?
We will see.
Be silent now.
Finish your supper.
But, Father...
Enough now!
But...
On with your work.
It is not enough!
Owen! Hold your tongue until
you have permission to speak!
I will speak against
injustice anywhere,
with permission or without it.
Not in this house.
In this house
and outside, sir.
Leave the table.
I will leave the house.
Gwil! Tell your
father you're sorry.
I'm not sorry.
I am with you. We can find
lodgings in the village.
Gwilym.
All of you, then?
For the last time,
sit down,
finish your supper.
I will say no more.
We are not questioning
your authority, sir,
but if manners prevent
our speaking the truth,
we will be without manners.
Get your clothes and go.
I am going with them
to look after them.
Hold your tongue, girl!
Get on with your dishes!
[Clink]
Ah-choo!
Yes, my son.
I know you are there.
The men have struck.
[Bells Ringing]
What does it mean,
Mr. Gruffydd?
It means that
something has gone
out of this valley
that may never be replaced.
Home to your
father and mother, boy.
They'll need you today.
22 weeks the men
were out, as the strike
moved into winter.
It was strange to go
out into the street
and find the men there
in the daytime.
It had a feeling
of fright in it,
and always the mood of
the men grew uglier,
as empty bellies
and desperation
began to conquer reason.
Any man who was
not their friend
became their enemy.
They knew that my father
had opposed the strike,
and now it was they
who opposed him.
[Glass Breaks]
[Smack]
Huw,
there's a meeting of the men
in the hills tonight, is it?
Yes, Mama.
You will take me there.
Oh, no, Mama.
It is no place
for women.
There's a place
for this woman
there tonight,
upon my soul.
Wait, wait till you hear me.
I am Beth Morgan,
as you damn well know.
I have come to tell you
what I think of you all
because you're talking
against my husband!
You're a lot of cowards
to go against him!
He would do
nothing against you,
and you know it well!
How some of you,
you smug-faced hypocrites,
can sit in the same chapel
with him I cannot tell.
To say he's with the owners
is not only nonsense,
but downright wickedness!
There's one thing
more I've got to say,
and it is this,
if harm comes to my Gwilym,
I'll find out the men,
and I will kill them
with my two hands,
and this I will swear
by God Almighty!
[Murmuring]
Lanto, help!
Help!
Help! Help!
Hold on, Mama!
They've heard us!
They're coming!
Ahh.
He was awake just now.
Shh.
He'll do, then.
But it's beyond me
to say why!
You're breeding horses
in this family, Mr. Morgan.
Ha!
This boy should be in
his coffin, for my part.
He's a Morgan,
then, is it, sir?
Eh.
He should be fed
now, Mrs. Ivor,
a little soup
and some warm smile.
Ahhh.
Yes.
Ah!
Horse!
Well, good day.
Wait, wait, wait.
Huw was awake.
He spoke to Bron.
How long for
the little one?
It's hard to tell.
His legs were frozen
to the bone.
A year,
two year like that,
but I can't promise
he'll ever walk again!
Nature must
take her course!
Mind your tongue!
I think he heard you.
Where is the light
I thought to see in your eye?
Are you afraid, boy?
Hmm?
You heard what
the doctor said?
Yes, sir.
And you believed it?
You want to walk again,
don't you?
Yes, sir.
Then you must have faith,
and if you have,
you will walk again
no matter what
all the doctors say.
But he said nature
must take her course.
"Nature is
the handmaiden
of the Lord."
I remember one
or two occasions
when she was given orders
to change her course.
You know your
scriptures, boy.
Yes, sir.
Then you know that
what's been done before
can be done again,
for you.
Do you believe me, Huw?
Yes, sir.
Good.
You will see
the first daffodil
out on the mountain.
Will you?
Indeed I will, sir.
Then you will.
I could almost wish
that I were lying
there in your place,
if it meant
reading this book again
for the first time.
Treasure Island.
Mr. Gruffydd?
I couldn't let you go
without thanking you.
It was only my duty, girl.
No. It was more than duty.
Yes, Huw's a fine boy,
and you're a fine family.
Um, you'd better be
going in now. You'll
catch your death.
Yes.
Will you be
coming to supper soon?
Uh, yes, later,
when you're finished
with doctors and such, huh?
I will hurry them away, then.
Good.
"Squire Trelawney,
Dr. Livesey,
"and the rest
of these gentlemen,
having asked me to write down
the whole particulars
about Treasure Island
from the beginning
to the end,
keeping nothing back but
the bearings of the island,
and that only because
there is still treasure
not yet lifted,
I take up my pen
in the year of grace 1785,
and go back to the time
when my father kept
the Admiral Benbow Inn..."
All the noble books
which have lived in
my mind ever since,
and always I hoped
and kept my faith.
For the first months,
my mother was still upstairs,
and we could talk
to each other with tappings.
[Chirp]
[Huw Whistling]
[Cackling]
Spring?
There you are, girl.
Easy.
There you are.
Wait.
It's the old snow got into it.
[Singing in Welsh]
Oh, Gwilym.
There is a wife you have,
resting in her bed
and letting strangers
care for her family.
There is a wife
I have, then.
Go along with you, boy.
[Singing in Welsh]
Will you say something,
Mother?
Go on. Say something.
But what...
What'll I say?
You found plenty to say
the last time you spoke.
It should be easier now,
with friends.
Well...
Well, come and eat,
everyone.
Smoke is it, boys.
Lanto.
I haven't seen you
in chapel lately.
I have been too busy.
What business,
may I ask?
Mine.
Only asking
a civil question, I was.
And having
a civil answer.
I have been busy
with the union.
Unions are the work
of the devil.
You will come
to no good end.
At least
I am not sitting on it,
talking rubbish in chapel.
Look here...
Oh, leave it,
or I'll say something
to be sorry.
This is a matter
that requires airing.
Lanto, why do you think
we at the chapel talk rubbish?
My remark was
not aimed at you.
Then aim it.
Very well.
Because you make
yourselves out to be
shepherds of the flock,
and yet you allow your sheep
to live in filth and poverty,
and if they try
and raise their
voices against it,
you calm them by telling
them their suffering
is the will of God.
Sheep, indeed.
Are we sheep to be
herded and sheared
by a handful of owners?
I was taught man
was made in the image
of God, not a sheep.
I haven't expressed
my views around here
because I haven't had
any wish to interfere
in a family disagreement.
You have
my permission
to speak.
Very well, then.
Here is what I think.
First, have your union.
You need it.
Alone, you are weak.
Together, you're strong.
But remember
that with strength
goes responsibility,
to others
and yourselves,
for you cannot conquer
injustice with more injustice,
only with justice
and the help of God.
Are you coming outside
your position in life,
Mr. Gruffydd?
Your business
is spiritual.
My business is anything
that comes between man
and the spirit of God.
The deacons shall hear
that you've been
preaching socialism!
Mr. Parry!
Loose the old devil's teeth!
He is our guest!
Beth, a pint
of home brew
for Mr. Parry.
I'll give him a clout
with a frying pan!
Oh!
Miss Jenkins!
A sweet song!
The harp, is it?
Come on, men.
Get in here.
Now, look.
A little song...
Angharad.
Mr. Gruffydd,
will we always be
in your debt,
now you have made
us a family again?
Here. Let me.
Oh, your hands.
There's a pity.
No matter.
Have you ever been
down the collieries?
10 years.
10 years?
While I was studying.
A bit of soap now.
Oh, don't bother,
please.
There's a man
for you, spoiling
his good handkerchief.
Look, now,
you are king
in the chapel,
but I will be queen
in my own kitchen.
You will be queen
wherever you walk.
What does that mean?
I should not
have said it.
Why?
I have no right
to speak to you so.
Mr. Gruffydd?
If the right is mine to give,
you have it.
[Horn Blowing]
Then the strike was settled,
with the help
of Mr. Gruffydd
and my father.
Work again,
work to wipe out the memory
of idleness and hardship.
The men were happy going
up the hill that morning.
1 and 9.
1 and 10!
[Horn Blowing]
But not all of them,
for there were too many now
for the jobs open,
and some learned
that never again
would there be work for them
in their own valley.
It is the same all over
South Wales, it is.
Father.
In Cardiff, the men are
standing in line to have
bread from the government.
Not for us, eh, lad?
We will have our
share of the box
and go,
if you please, sir.
Where will you go?
America.
My share, too, Owen.
And mine.
No. Our own.
We will take
no charity.
Not charity, man, sense.
No, only our own.
Ahem.
[Sniff Sniff]
Say nothing of this
to your mother.
Let this day
be over first.
Never mind
saying nothing.
I heard.
America?
My babies.
Shall we have a chapter,
my sons?
What shall
we have, sir?
Isaiah 55.
Those two gone,
this is only
the beginning.
Then all of you will go.
One after the other,
all of you.
I will never
leave you, Mama.
Huw, boy, if you
should ever leave me,
I'll be sorry
I ever had babies.
Why did you
have them?
Indeed to goodness,
boy, why?
To keep my hands in water
and my face to the fire,
perhaps.
Whoa!
For Mr. Ivor Morgan.
From Windsor Castle it is.
"Mr. Ivor Morgan is
commanded to appear
before Her Majest..."
"Mr. Ivor Morgan
is commanded
to appear before
Her Majesty
at Windsor Castle
with chosen members
of his choir
the 14th of May
between the hours
of 3:00 and 5:00."
Yay!
God save the Queen!
To sing before the queen.
My son, I never thought
to see this beautiful day.
Idris, Owen, all of you,
fetch everyone from
all the valleys 'round.
Davy, over to
the other collieries.
Invite everyone.
It's a celebration,
tell them.
Lanto, down to the
Three Bells for beer.
Open house tonight
for all who will come.
[Cheering]
My sons,
you shall have a sendoff
worthy of the Morgans.
[Bell Rings]
Our heavenly Father,
I give thanks
from the heart
to live this day.
I give thanks for all I have,
and I do give thanks
for this new blessing,
for you are our father,
but we look to our
queen as our mother.
Comfort her in her
troubles, oh God,
and let her worries be
not more than she shall
bear at her age,
and grant that sweetness
and power and spirit
may be given to these
voices that shall sing
at her command.
Amen.
[Bell Rings]
♪ God save our
gracious queen ♪
♪ Long live our noble queen ♪
♪ God save our queen ♪
♪ Send her victorious ♪
♪ Happy and glorious ♪
Gwilym! Owen!
♪ Long to reign over us ♪
♪ God save our queen ♪
[Knock on Door]
Good morning,
dear Mr. Gruffydd.
There is good to see you.
Angharad is
at the market.
Angharad?
Oh, I've come for Huw.
For Huw?
The daffodils
are out, Mama.
Where are your
clothes, boy?
Under my pillow.
Your pillow?
For these months,
ready for today.
Come then, and you shall bring
back a posy fit for a queen
for your brave mother.
Indeed I will, sir.
Almost there, Huw.
Yes, sir.
Low bridge there.
Watch out.
It's fine.
All right.
Ha ha!
All right?
Yes, sir.
Easy it is, now.
There.
Cwm Rhondda.
But, Mr. Gruffydd...
You can walk,
Huw, if you try.
Come, lad.
You can walk.
Huw! Walk!
There's a good lad.
Come on.
See? Ha ha!
There's a good old man.
You've been lucky, Huw.
Lucky to suffer,
lucky to spend these
weary months in bed.
For so God has
given you a chance
to make spirit
within yourself,
and as your father
cleans his lamp
to have good light,
so keep clean
your spirit, huh?
How, sir?
By prayer, Huw.
And by prayer,
I don't mean
shouting and mumbling
and wallowing like a hog
in religious sentiment.
Prayer is only
another name for good,
clean, direct thinking.
When you pray, think.
Think well
what you're saying.
Make your thoughts into
things that are solid,
and that way,
your prayer will
have strength,
and that strength will
become a part of you,
body, mind,
and spirit.
And the first duty
of these new legs
is to get you
to chapel on Sunday.
Indeed they will, sir.
There's a good
old man again.
Give me your hand.
Come on now.
[Ringing]
[Choir Singing]
Will you please
remain in your places?
There's to be
a meeting
of the deacons.
Ceinwen Lewis!
Step forward!
Your sins have
found you out!
And now you must
pay the price of
all women like you.
You have brought
a child into the world
against the Commandment!
Prayer is wasted
on your sort!
You shall be cast out
into the outer darkness
till you have
learned your lesson!
Ceinwen Lewis,
do you admit your sin?
Yes.
Then prepare to suffer
your punishment!
Stop it!
Angharad!
Leave her alone,
you hypocrite!
Sit down, Mr. Morgan.
You...
Sit down!
[Sobbing]
How could you stand
there and watch them?
Cruel old men
groaning and nodding
to hurt her more.
That is not
the word of God.
"Go thou,
and sin no more,"
Jesus said!
Angharad!
You know your Bible
too well, life too little.
I know enough of life
to know that Ceinwen Lewis
is no worse than I am.
Angharad!
What do the deacons know?
What do you know
about what could
happen to a poor girl
when she loves
a man so much
that to lose sight of him
for a moment is torture?
Does that hurt you, Huw?
Easy, now.
Huw?
Angharad. Angharad!
I am a man now!
Kindly leave the kitchen!
Oh, so you're
a man now, is it?
Ow!
Ha ha ha!
Hey! Hey!
Blasphemy, sacrilege,
and hypocrisy!
Can't a man smoke
his pipe and read his
paper on the sabbath?
Oh, go and
blow your nose!
[Knock on Door]
Come in!
[Knock Knock]
What under the blaz...
Good morning, Morgan.
Good morning, Mr. Evans.
Sit down, sir.
Oh. Thank you.
Mr. Evans.
The mine owner himself.
Angharad.
Ahh.
Now to business, Morgan.
Yes, sir.
Uh...
I've come here on a very
delicate mission, Morgan.
No trouble, sir?
No, no, no. No trouble,
but it worries me.
Yes, sir.
I'm here to get
your permission
that my son lestyn
may have permission...
Ah-choo!
Bless you, Morgan.
Thank you, sir.
Now, where was I?
Permission.
Oh, yes. That my son lestyn
may have permission,
with your
daughter's permission,
to call upon her.
There we are.
We are a very proud
family, Mr. Evans.
Yes, yes, I know,
I know, Morgan,
but this is not
my doing, Morgan.
It's that young boy...
Mr. Evans, your son
has my permission
to speak to me.
Thank you.
Thank you, Morgan.
I'm very much
obliged to you.
Yes, sir. Yes, sir.
Good old Welsh blood,
you know, and all that
sort of thing.
I'm very much
obliged, Morgan.
Yes, sir. Yes, sir.
Good day, Morgan.
Beth! Beth!
Come, come, come.
My shoes. Get my shoes.
You, girl,
get up to your room.
Have you no modesty
left in you? Get up there.
Take your hand out...
My shoes! Find the shoes!
Why don't you get
your jackets on?
Get your...
[Knock on Door]
Mr. Morgan.
Sit down.
This is my wife
Mrs. Morgan.
How do you do?
Mr. Morgan,
I've come to ask
your permission
to speak to your
daughter Angharad.
These are my sons.
Yes. I know them.
Ah-choo!
God bless you.
[Clock Strikes 9:00]
You shouldn't be here.
I couldn't spend another
night without knowing.
What has happened?
Is anything wrong?
Wrong?
You know what I mean.
Why have you
changed towards me?
Why am I a stranger now?
Have I done anything?
No.
The blame is mine.
Your mother spoke
to me after chapel.
She's happy to think
you'll be having
plenty all your days.
Lestyn Evans.
You could do no better.
I don't want him!
I want you.
Angharad.
I have spent nights, too,
trying to think this out.
When I took up this work,
I knew what it meant.
It meant sacrifice
and devotion.
It meant making
it my whole life
to the...
To the exclusion
of everything else.
That I was perfectly
willing to do.
But to share it
with another...
Do you think
I will have you going
threadbare all your life,
depending on
the charity of others
for your good meals,
our children growing up
in cast-off clothing,
and ourselves
thanking God for parenthood
in a house full of bits?
No. I can bear
with such a life for
the sake of my work,
but I think
I'd start to kill
if I saw the white
come to your hair
20 years before its time.
Why?
Why would you
start to kill?
Are you a man
or a saint?
I am no saint,
but I have a duty
towards you.
Let me do it.
[Bell Ringing]
Is there to be no singing
for my daughter's wedding,
Dai Bando?
[Singing in Welsh]
Now, then,
the bathtub holds
100 gallons.
"A" fills it at the rate
of 20 gallons a minute
and "B" at the rate
of 10 gallons a minute.
Got that, Mr. Morgan?
20 and 10 gallons.
Yes, sir.
Now, then,
"C" is a hole that empties it
at the rate of 5
gallons a minute.
How long to fill the tub?
Hmm.
Ha ha ha!
They're silly.
Trying to fill a bathtub
full of holes, indeed.
A sum it is, girl, a sum,
a problem for the mind,
for his examination
into school next month.
That old national school,
just silly they are with
their sums.
Who would pour water
in a bathtub full of holes?
Who would think of it?
Only a madman.
It is to see if the boy
can calculate, girl.
Figures, nothing else.
How many gallons
and how long?
In a bathtub
full of holes.
Now I know why I have
such a tribe of sons.
It is you,
Beth Morgan,
is the cause.
Look you, Mr. Gruffydd,
have you something else?
The decimal point.
The decimal point, then.
And peace to my house!
Go and scratch.
Uh, it's getting late.
I've got to get along.
We'll follow
the decimal point
tomorrow night.
Yes, sir.
Good night.
Good night,
Mrs. Morgan.
Good night, Mr. Gruffydd.
Who is there that
cannot look back
and remember his first day
at a new school?
To go alone the long
walk over the hills
to the next valley,
the first of my family
to have the privilege
of attending
a national school.
So you're the new boy?
Yes, sir.
You're late.
What a dirty
little sweep it is.
[Laughter]
Who are your people?
Where are you from?
Cwm Rhondda.
Cwm Rhondda?
Oh, a little genius
from the coal pits,
and they expect me to
make a scholar of it.
All right, come in.
Were you
brought up in stables?
[Laughter]
Well, shut the door.
Your boots are muddy.
They were clean
when I left home.
You will address me
as sir, or I'll put
a stick about your back.
Now, sit down here.
Yes, sir.
Ha ha ha!
[Laughter]
Come here,
you dirty little sweep.
What have we here?
A pencil box.
Pretty, too.
Hey, you broke
my pencil box!
[Shrieking]
Mervyn, Mervyn, stop it!
You'll hurt him!
Hit him! Hit him!
I... I fell
on the mountain.
Did you win, Huw?
No.
Lanto!
Fetch Dai Bando.
Dai Bando, is it?
Are you willing to go
to school tomorrow?
Yes, sir.
Good.
From tonight,
you shall get a penny for
every mark on your face,
sixpence for a bloody nose,
a shilling for a black eye,
and two shillings
for a broken nose.
Gwilym, stop it.
Fight again,
and when you come home,
not another look
will you get from me,
not another word.
Break your own nose, then.
Break your mother's heart.
A boy must fight, Beth.
Fight? Fight, is it?
Another beating like that
and he would walk home dead.
Beating?
He's had no beating.
A hiding, yes,
but no beating.
Give the boy time, it will be
he that's giving the beating,
is it?
Dai Bando,
come into the house.
Good evening, Mrs. Morgan.
Good Evening, Mrs. Morgan.
Leave off your hat.
Dai Bando is going
to teach you to box, Huw.
To fight first.
Too many call themselves
boxers who are not even
fighters.
Boxing is an art, is it?
It is. It is.
Go along with you, girl.
A cup of tea for the men,
is it?
Tea?
Tea? No tea, Mrs. Morgan.
In training, he is.
A glass of beer
if you please.
Baths full of holes,
and now prizefighters.
Get him!
Come on!
Come on, get him, Mervyn!
Get up! Get up!
Hit him!
Knock him down, Mervyn!
Hit him, Mervyn!
Our wild little
coal-mining friend
has been indulging
in his favorite
sport again, eh?
Mr. Phillips,
make a back, please.
I refuse, sir.
Make a back,
Mr. Phillips!
I refuse, sir!
Mr. Mills,
make a back.
Here. Put this in
between your teeth.
Bite it hard.
Well, the scholar!
[Whimpering]
Huw!
Lad!
I'll go to my death.
You got that in school?
He's cut you to the bone.
Who was it?
Mr. Jonas?
We'll have a word
with him.
No.
Why not?
I broke the rule
when I fought.
There's no rule
for that.
But he warned me.
Rubbish, boy!
Wait, Davy.
This is Huw's affair.
He shall decide.
Say the word, lad,
and we will have the
bones hot from his flesh.
No. Leave him alone.
I think our baby brother
is becoming quite a man.
These denominations
are used in measuring
distances and...
Yes?
Right!
Good morning,
Mister...
Jonas.
Mr. Jonas.
We have come to
the right place, indeed.
Ha ha ha!
What can I
do for you?
A man is never
too old to learn,
is it, Mr. Jonas?
No.
I was in school
myself once,
but no great one
for knowledge.
Look here,
what do you want?
Knowledge.
How would you go about
taking the measurement
of a stick, Mr. Jonas?
By its length, of course.
And how would you
measure a man
who would use a stick
on a boy 1/3 his size?
Tell us.
Now, you are good
in the use of a stick,
but boxing
is my subject,
according to the rules
laid down by the good
Marquis of Queensberry.
God rest his soul.
And happy I am to pass
on my knowledge to you.
Mr. Motshill!
All right, get him
into position, now.
Now, look,
to make a good boxer,
you must have a good
right hand, you see?
Now, you see,
that is how you
will punish your man,
with a right
and a left.
The gentleman
is talking to you.
Raise him.
Come on, come on.
Up, up, up.
Position again.
Could I have your attention,
boys and girls?
I am not accustomed
to speaking in public.
Only public houses.
But this, never use.
It's against the rules.
Break a man's nose.
Now, then...
I'm afraid he will
never make a boxer.
No aptitude
for knowledge.
[Whistle Blowing]
[Bell Clanging]
Mr. Gruffydd!
Ivor fell under a tram,
lower level.
[Crying]
Ivor!
[Praying in Welsh]
We have our first
grandson, Gwil.
Give one
and take the other.
Tell that to that
girl up there!
She'll have an answer for you.
Do not kindle
the wrath.
To hell with the wrath!
And I'm saying it
plain to be heard.
Ah, 'tis good.
With honors, then.
Our son is a scholar.
What is it, Huw?
I can't make
sense with it.
Latin it is.
Latin, is it? Why not good
Welsh or even English?
It is the fashion.
Fashion.
Frenchies, decimal points,
and bathtubs full of holes.
My poor Huw,
they've stuffed
your head with Latin.
Beth, my old beauty,
you, a black eye, is it?
Go ahead, shout!
Wake up the baby, then.
There is beautiful.
The image of my father,
he is.
What bloody nonsense.
Now then, Huw,
what will it be?
To Cardiff to school,
then the university
to be a lawyer,
is it, or a doctor?
Dr. Huw Morgan.
Well, Uncle Huw,
that will be
something special.
Yes, indeed,
with a lovely
horse and trap
and a good black suit
and a shirt with starch.
Oh, there is good,
my little one.
Now then, a glass
of buttermilk for you
with all your knowledge.
Yes, Mother,
and some of
Bron's shortcake.
Oh, and my shortcake
is to be fed to the pigs,
is it?
No, only I finished
yours yesterday.
Today is
shortcake day
with Bron.
I'm sorry, Huw,
only currant bread
I made today.
Nobody to eat it now.
Oh, Mother,
I'm lonely without him.
I put his boots
and clothes ready
every night,
but they're there
still in the morning.
There is lonely I am.
Gwil, I will have Bron here
to live if she will come.
Not Bron.
One mistress
in the house.
Now, Huw,
what will it be?
I will go down
the colliery
with you, sir.
Have sense, boy.
The colliery is
no place for you.
Why not try for
a respectable job?
Respectable?
Are you and his brothers
a lot of old jailbirds?
Leave it now, Beth.
I only want
the best for the boy.
If he is as good a man
as you and his brothers,
I will rest happy.
I'm thinking of
the boy's future.
It was different
in our day,
there was good money
and fair play for all.
But Huw is a scholar.
Why take brains
down a coal mine?
I would rather, sir.
All right.
Decide for yourself,
but blame yourself
if you are wrong.
The colliery, sir.
All right.
The colliery it is.
Good.
Where are you going?
To get drunk!
Bron?
I am going down
the colliery.
Oh, the colliery,
is it?
The old coal will be
shaking in its seam.
Bron...
Bro... Bron, would you have me
to live in this house
and have my wages?
Your home is
with your mother.
It was she who sent me.
From pity?
No, from sense.
If you put clothes
night and morning,
let them be
my clothes.
Good old man.
Yes or no, Bron?
Yes.
Goo... Good.
Good. I will
get my bed.
[Singing in Welsh]
[Whistle Blowing]
So it is a man now, is it?
And could I carry
such a man?
Lanto!
Ha ha ha!
5 shillings.
7 and tuppence.
Move along!
Thanks.
3 shillings.
2.09.
£1.02.
£2. 10.
Discharged, Morgan.
Move along.
£2. 10.
Discharged, Morgan.
£1. 10.
And so it came
to lanto and Davy,
the best workers
in the colliery
but too highly paid
to compete with poorer,
more desperate men.
[Bell Ringing]
Will you read us
a chapter, Father?
Yes, my son.
"The Lord is my shepherd,
I shall not want.
He maketh me to lie down
in green pastures.
He leadeth me
beside the still waters.
He restoreth my soul.
He leadeth me in the paths
of righteousness
for his name's sake.
Yea, though I walk
through the valley
of the shadow of death,
I will fear no evil
for thou art with me.
Thy rod and thy staff,
they comfort me.
Thou preparest
a table before me
in the presence
of mine enemies.
Thou anointest
my head with oil."
[Door Closes]
"My cup runneth over."
One line to Owen and Gwil,
down to Cape Town to Angharad,
over here to Canada to lanto,
and down here to Davy
in New Zealand.
And you are the star,
shining on them
from this house
all the way
across the continents
and the oceans.
All the way?
How far am I shining
if you can put it all
on a little piece of paper?
Now, a map it is,
my old beauty.
A picture of the world
to show you where they are.
I know where they are
without any old maps
or scratches
or spiders
or pencils.
They are in the house.
Then Angharad came
back from Cape Town
without her husband.
She did not come to us
but stayed at
the big Evans house,
her house on top of the hill.
To see Mrs. Evans,
please.
Who is it?
Huw Morgan.
Her brother, is it?
Come in.
Why, Huw...
Mrs. Nicholas,
will you bring
some tea, please?
Sit down, Huw.
There is grown you are,
and changed.
You, too.
I look ill and ought
to take care of myself.
Everyone coming in
the house says so,
so you say it, too,
and let us finish with it.
But tell me all the news.
How is...
How are all the boys
and girls we used to know?
Well,
the Jenkins girls
are married.
Maldwyn Hughes has
gone to be a doctor.
Rhys Howell is in
a solicitor's office,
and he's sending home
10 shillings a week.
And Mr. Gruffydd,
is still first up
and last to bed.
How is he, Huw?
Not as he was.
Is he ill?
Inside, in his eyes
and in his voice.
Like you.
Please go home, Huw.
I'm sorry.
Now then, Mrs. Evans.
Tea, is it?
Leave it,
Mrs. Nicholas.
I will pour.
Well!
I always did the pouring
for Mr. Lestyn's poor mother.
I will pour.
Yes, Mrs. Evans.
A new mistress
is like new sheets,
yes, a little bit stiff,
but washings to come.
Why do you
have her here?
37 years with the family,
or so she tells me
60 times a day.
Have some tea, Huw.
You don't
want me to go?
No. No, Huw.
I'm sorry
for being nasty.
Please stay.
Oh, Huw!
I tried to tell
Mother, but...
[Sobbing]
Not for me to say.
Only the housekeeper I am.
37 years in the family
and living to
curse the day!
It will not
surprise me any day
to see the old master
rise white from his grave.
'Tis only the gravestone
is holding him down,
I will swear.
Then what is it,
Mrs. Nicholas?
Divorce.
Divorce!
Saying nothing I am,
but that is what
is in her mind.
She is here without
her husband, is it?
And why?
'Tis because
she is in love
with this preacher.
Preacher, I said!
Mr. Gruffydd it is.
But Mr. Gruffydd has
not been near the house.
What difference
is that, girl?
Get on with your work!
We will not say
a word, Mrs. Nicholas.
Oh, no!
No, no!
Liar! Liar!
You're a filthy liar!
[Jeering and Shouting]
Come on!
Get him!
Come on, Roger!
Get him, Roger!
Let up!
Let me at him!
Liar! Liar! Liar!
As the slag had spread
over my valley,
so now a blackness spread
over the minds of its people.
For the first time
in my memory,
our front door was shut
tight in the daytime.
Dada?
Well, Huw,
trouble with the
philistines, is it?
Huw, what is it now?
Look at your hands.
Evan John,
he said things
about Angharad
and Mr. Gruffydd.
The children, too.
You were right, my son.
I will be back
for breakfast.
You will not
go to chapel?
No.
And if they
do this thing,
I will never set foot
in the chapel again
as long as I live.
I will have
the sheets warm
on your bed.
There is an old
beauty you are.
Go and scratch, boy.
What is this about
the chapel, Mother?
Tonight after
the service,
a deacons' meeting
over Angharad.
Angharad?
But she has
done nothing.
Nothing is enough for people
who have minds like cesspools.
Oh, Huw, my little one,
I hope when you're grown
their tongues will
be slower to hurt.
But will Angharad
have to be
at the meeting?
No, none of us
will be there.
But the disgrace
will not stay away.
I will go, Mother.
[Singing in Welsh]
This is the last time
I will talk in this chapel.
I am leaving the valley
with regret
toward those who
have helped me here
and who have
let me help them.
But,
for the rest of you,
those of you who
have only proved
that I have wasted
my time among you,
I have only this to say.
There is not
one among you
who has had
the courage to come to me
and accuse me of wrongdoing.
And yet, by any standard,
if there has been a sin,
I am the one
who should be
branded the sinner.
Will anyone raise
his voice here now
to accuse me?
No.
You're cowards, too,
as well as hypocrites.
But I don't blame you.
The fault is mine
as much as yours.
The idle tongues,
the poverty of mind
which you have shown
mean that I have failed
to reach most of you
with the lesson
I was given to teach.
Huw?
I thought,
when I was a young man,
that I would conquer
the world with truth.
I thought I would
lead an army greater than
Alexander ever dreamed of,
not to conquer nations
but to liberate mankind...
Yes, sir.
...with truth
and the golden
sound of the word.
But only a few
of them heard.
Only a few
of you understood.
The rest of you put on
black and sat in chapel!
Why do you come here?
Why do you dress
your hypocrisy in black
and parade before
your God on Sunday?
From love?
No.
For you've shown
that your hearts
are too withered
to receive the love
of your Divine Father.
I know why you've come.
I've seen it in your faces
Sunday after Sunday
as I've stood
here before you.
Fear has brought you here,
horrible,
superstitious fear.
Fear of divine retribution.
A bolt of fire
from the skies,
the vengeance of the Lord
and the justice of God.
But you have forgotten
the love of Jesus.
You disregard
his sacrifice.
Death, fear, flames,
horror, and black clothes!
Hold your meeting, then.
But know if you do
this in the name of God
and in the house of God,
you blaspheme against
Him and His word.
Wait!
There is a meeting,
Master Morgan.
Well, Huw.
I'm glad you've come.
Thank you, sir.
Is there
anything I can do?
Indeed there is.
You can do me
a great service.
This watch,
my father gave it to me
when I entered the ministry.
It's marked time
we both loved.
Take it.
Oh, no, sir.
A service I said
you'd be doing me.
No need for us
to shake hands.
We will live in
the minds of each other.
Mr. Gruffydd,
won't you see
Angharad before you go?
She wants you to.
No.
If I were to
see her again,
I couldn't find the
strength to leave her.
Goodbye, Huw.
And there's a good
old man you are.
[Whistle Blowing]
[Crowd Shouting]
What is it now?
Fire or flood or what?
Cave-in, they're saying.
Take me up by there.
What good in
the darkness of a mine?
Your eyes are no longer
good in the daylight
from the blows you
have taken in the ring.
I can still swing a pick
deeper than any man.
Take me up there.
[Explosion]
[Whistle Blowing]
Bron! Bron! Gwilym!
Those of you
with relatives.
Let them to the pit.
Gwilym Morgan?
Not yet, sir.
Mr. Gruffydd,
on the lower level he was.
[Coughing]
My father?
Not yet, Mrs. Evans.
[Crying]
[Woman Screams]
[Crying and Moaning]
[Church Bell Ringing]
Angharad.
Who is for Gwilym Morgan
and the others?
I, for one.
He is the blood
of my heart.
Come, Cyfartha.
'Tis a coward I am,
but I will hold
your coat.
[Singing in Welsh]
Dada!
[Echoing] Dada! Dada!
Huw.
Lad.
Dada! Dada!
Dada!
Huw.
Dada.
Mr. Gruffydd!
There's a good
old man you are.
He came to me just now.
Ivor was with him.
He spoke to me
and told me of
the glory he had seen.
Look.
[Church Bell Ringing]
[Singing in Welsh]
Men like my father cannot die.
They are with me still,
real in memory
as they were in flesh,
loving and beloved forever.
How green was my valley then.
[Singing in Welsh]
[Church Bell Ringing}
ENGLISH - US - PSDH